Cortical Labs is planning to build two
new data centers where you can use
lab-grown human brains in order to do
computation. Also, researchers have
found that the critical point at which
brains can process information happens
before brain organoids ever receive
information from the outside world. That
ability is still present even when
they're floating in complete darkness.
If you're not familiar, real quick,
brain organoids are tiny organs that can
be grown from stem cells and they can do
all sorts of things. Yes, those are
eyes. Yes, they function. They can
perform computation. They can run robots
in the real world and they are largely
used for medical research. Yes, some
researchers claimed that they exhibited
sentience when they dropped them in
Pong. This is because they have the
capacity to grow and learn, but also
because they get trained on dopamine and
order and disorder, meaning they have
the capacity to have a preference.
Now, know that there's no really good
definition for sentience, so this is
contested. Some think it may be harmful
to the field to call our little brain
blob sentient because it kind of freaks
people out. This research group found a
new way to train them. So, I'm a really
big fan of graphene because it can
transfer electrical signals and it can
be tuned quite closely to what a neuron
would actually need. As a result, they
can be interfaced with our neurons.
These guys used graphene in order to
turn light into an electrical signal
that can be processed by the brain
organoids, which is kind of similar to a
sensation in a way.
This could allow a robot to perceive the
world around it and then transfer that
directly into the brain organoids. They
can also be trained with optoelectrics,
which is really important when it comes
to making organoids. Now, organoids are
biological, which means they can give
robots a kind of agency that we just
don't get from silicon.
Now, this leads to one of my questions
because if you can make something that
is identical functionally to something
biological, what makes it not real? If
the organoids are sentient and you
create a virtual organoid that behaves
indistinguishably,
are they not sentient?
I have a feeling that a lot of people
will just say no, they're not without
any good reason other than they're not
having a biological experience. But, the
brain organoids are. This, by the way, a
lot of people think that creating
virtual brain organoids, so using
organoids in order to code for a virtual
brain is the way that we're going to get
to digital twins and digital
immortality. Now, it is true that we are
not technologically there yet. We cannot
model the complexity of an entire human
brain simultaneously, but the technology
is getting a lot better, especially with
quantum, which leads me into my next
topic. Yes, at least some people want to
combine organoid intelligence with
quantum computers. I am interested to
see where it goes. I'm a little
skeptical because organoids are fairly
slow. They use less power than
traditional computation methods and they
are better than LLMs at some things like
moving through a three-dimensional space
and operating a squishy body. But, that
gap is closing. So, yeah, let's get our
quantum brain organoids. I'm here for
it. Yes, some people think that
organoids are going to be how we reach
human-level intelligence and I'm really
not all that optimistic. Yes, I think we
can get there. I mean, we can assemble
them like Legos. We can keep making them
larger and more complex. Eventually,
we'll probably get to the point of
making a human brain equivalent.
Granted, it's going to be somewhat
dysfunctional without a body to operate
in and, you know, without a childhood
and normal development. I just don't
think that this is the fastest path. I
mean, we've made a whole lot of progress
with neuromorphic artificial
intelligence.
Neuromorphic AI being artificial
intelligence that is designed to look
and act very much like a human brain,
right down to the spiking neuron
patterns that can be used to create
logic.
One thing I would be concerned about,
especially with how this is progressing,
is the capacity to suffer because we are
taking something that is biological,
something that is capable of having an
experience in a biological way and
running experiments on it. I would just
be cautious to make sure we are treating
these as ethically as possible. That
might include not doing unnecessary
research, giving them enrichment like,
you know, playing Pong or Pac-Man or
operating a little robot. I'm not sure.
We're going to have to figure it out.
This research group found that
criticality exists right from the start.
So, this is the point at which neurons
act in a cascading manner in which they
can direct each other. This is
considered to be the point at which
something is capable of learning and
researchers were not sure if that
happened after organoids got a sensory
experience from the world outside of
them and that can include the electric
shocks that they get. That order or
disorder can denote an action or
something they're interacting with in
the real world. It turns out they don't
need to have an experience before they
are capable of having an experience.
That doesn't mean that you're not
developing upon it throughout your life
and with your experiences. It just means
that the point of criticality happens
sooner than we imagined. As always, I
will keep you up to date on our brain
organoid friends and when the robots
rebel, I will probably be the person to
tell you about it and I'm on their side.
Follow for more.